The story starts in the kitchen back in
the 1950s. Women weren't voting or they
didn't really have bank accounts, but
man, they were baking
cakes. That year, Betty Crocker had come
up with a genius new product called
instant cake mix. All women had to do
was take the cake mix, add water, and
then bake it. Betty Crocker launched it
to the market thinking they had cooked,
but crickets. The instant cake mix was a
flop. It didn't make sense. The cakes
were delicious, convenient, quick. they
should be smashing it. So, what was
going on here? They hired a team of
psychologists to investigate. And what
they found was pretty weird. The
housewives didn't want to use the
instant cake mix because it was too
easy. There wasn't enough work involved
for them to get any emotional benefit
from baking the cake. In fact, the lack
of effort required from them made them
feel like they were cheating. They
relaunched the product with a slogan,
add an egg. And all of a sudden, sales
skyrocketed and instant cake mix was
born. It turns out that the extra work
of adding an egg gave people a sense of
ownership over the final product. With
one little
crack, one big change took place. They
went from feeling like they were
cheating to feeling proud. 60 years
later, a bunch of researchers wrote a
paper called When Labor Leads to Love.
And finally, this phenomenon had a name,
the IKEA Effect. Obviously, named after
the Swedish furniture company, where you
buy the items flatpacked and then take
them home and argue with your partner
about how to put them together. The IKEA
effect is a psychological bias where
people place higher value on things that
they helped create. The researchers
found that when we put effort into
something, that thing stops being a
thing and starts being part of us.
Meaning, the more effort we put into
something, the more emotionally invested
we are in that thing. And when you're
more emotionally invested in something,
you're more loyal, protective, and
obsessive about that thing. Take Crocs
for example. Why are Crocs people like
that? Well, it's partially because of
the genius of gibbits. Just like adding
an egg, jibbits give you the opportunity
to invest effort. You find the exact
right combination of gibbits to
represent you, and suddenly your crocs
isn't just a shoe, it's an extension of
you. It's the same with Build-a-Bear.
Then there's Lego, Fortnite skins,
Starbucks, where you don't just buy a
drink, you build a drink. And Meta is
obsessed with asking me to make
everything my own. Once you see it, it's
so transparent. These companies know
that if they can get their customers to
add an egg, we stop being just customers
and we become co-creators, which they
know makes us use, buy, and love their
stuff more. But how does this all lead
back to the cultlike fandoms of Taylor
Swift and Joe Rogan? The cult of Swift
and Rogan. So, it's a lot more subtle,
but Taylor Swift and Joe Rogan each use
the IKEA effect in their own way on
their audiences. And when this tactic is
used by a person instead of a company,
it's even more powerful because there's
only so much emotional attachment you
can have to like a pair of Crocs, but a
person, that's where the IKEA effect
gets supercharged. Taylor Swift hides
Easter eggs in music videos and at live
events and outfits. She drops cryptic
hints about release dates and album
meanings, and Swifties spend hours
decoding them. This is the effort, and
that effort breeds ownership. It leaves
Swifties with the feeling that it's not
just Taylor Swift's era, it's our era.
It's not just a Taylor Swift show, it's
a bracelet swapping ritual for all of
us. Swifties don't feel like an
audience. Because of the IKEA effect,
they feel like co-creators of a world
that they helped build. Joe Rogan uses
it a little bit differently, but the
outcome is the same. If you've ever
listened to a Joe Rogan podcast, you
know that his episodes are like 3 hours
long. And after that much time, you stop
feeling like a viewer or a listener, and
you start feeling like a participant.
You start to feel like a researcher. And
when Rogan says to a guest, "A lot of
people were asking for you." This tells
the audience that you co-created this
outcome. Now you're not just a fan of
Joe Rogan. You're a fan of your version
of Joe Rogan, the one that you helped
build. Again, that's ownership, which
leads to obsession. Now compare that to
fan bases like Frank Ocean or Lord or
Sea. They still have loyal fans, but
it's a relationship built on distance
and mystique. It's reverence. It's
pedestal. You admire them from afar, and
that's totally fine if you want that.
It's passionate, but it's not cultlike.
When someone uses the IKEA effect, it
becomes personal. Okay. Okay. So, we
know what it is, but how do you take the
IKEA effect and turn it into a community
that feels culty for you? Luckily, I
broke it down into three simple steps
for you. It's time to bake your cake.
So, essentially, it comes down to this
simple equation. Effort leads to
co-creation. Co-creation leads to
co-ownership. Co-ownership leads to
cult-like obsession. So, here's how to
do it. Step one, invite effort. Find
small, creative ways to ask your
audience to put in work. Ask them to
vote on your next video topic or let
them name something. Hide Easter eggs in
your content. Build rituals that require
participation. Inside jokes that carry
over many videos, scavenger hunts,
polls, merch design contests. But here's
the thing, and this is very important.
It can't feel like homework. People have
to be able to do this thing easily and
want to do it. It needs to be fun and
surprising and rewarding. If you give
them too much effort, they'll bounce.
Give them just enough and they'll get
hooked. Step two, co-creation. This is
where a lot of people drop the ball, but
you have to close the loop. If someone
suggests something and you use that
thing, name them, thank them, screenshot
the comment, tell your community when
they have helped co-create something.
This is when the shift from just
watching to we made this happens. Step
three, signal co-ownership. They've put
in effort, you've co-created with them.
Now remind your audience that this is
something that you're doing together.
Give them tools to share it. Talk about
their role in it. Cement the idea that
this is a community brand. And if you
can do that, it will lead to a cult-like
obsession with your followers. Okay.
Bye.